And we pick up with we're almost at the משנה Mishna on
כ"ז עמוד ב'. Chaf Zayin Amud Beis. We pick up with אמר
רבי אליעזר. Amar Rabbi Eliezer. So we're dealing with all these interesting
questions about if you put the דם Dam on the wrong place
of the מזבח, Mizbeach, does it do absolutely nothing and so much
nothing that you can go get other דם Dam and put it
on, or does it make the
קרבן, Korban,
or does it say that basically the קרבן Korban is technically valid
but you can't eat the meat? So that's the question. And then
even if it did absolutely nothing and you could get more דם,
Dam, it might have done enough that you can't reuse the דם
Dam on the מזבח. Mizbeach. And that was the issues we dealt
with yesterday. So let's just finish up these discussions. אמר רבי אליעזר
Amar Rabbi Eliezer about six lines before the lines get wide on
כ"ז עמוד ב'. Chaf Zayin Amud Beis. מזבח
הפנימי מקדש פסולים. Mizbeach Hapnimi mekadesh psulim. Oh, so within this discussion
we had yesterday as a bit of a digression, we discussed this
idea about
when you do a valid הקרבה hakravah when it's not brought properly
the קרבן, korban, but if the limbs were still put on the
altar, you don't take them off of the altar except with a
very small number of exceptions. And the questions are what were the
exceptions? And that was a debate. Okay, but anyway, because we raised
that issue, we're saying like this: the inner altar
similarly sanctifies invalid things to say that if they go up on
the מזבח, mizbeach, they don't go down. So that means if you
take the blood and you bring it on the inner altar, which
actually invalidates the blood—it says that a blood of an outer חטאת
chatas that's brought inside, it invalidates it—nevertheless, even though you've invalidated the
blood and you put it if you put it on the inner
altar and then you put the limbs, let's say, on the outer
altar, you can now go ahead and leave them there. You don't
have to take them off, which is a pretty funny idea. But
okay, now, if you said, if you remember, there's a debate of
תנאים. Tannaim. According to one opinion, even if you spilled the blood,
if you left the limbs on the altar, you don't have to
take them off. So according to that, that's not such a חידוש
chiddush here. Okay, you brought it inside, you invalidated it, it's not
about the weight of the inner altar, it's really the fact that
even if you spilled the blood, once you put the limbs on,
you don't take them off. But the גמרא Gemara is making this
assertion according to the position that if you spilled the blood, you
have to take the limbs down. You need the blood to get
to the altar to allow you to keep the limbs on the
top.
And it could be in the wrong place in the altar, above,
below, etc. And here it's saying it could even be on the
inner altar. That does enough to validate the קרבן—again, korban not to
say that anybody fulfilled their obligation or you could eat the meat,
etc.—but enough that the blood got to some altar that if the
limbs go up, you don't have to take them down. מזבח הפנימי,
Mizbeach Hapnimi, even the inner altar, מקדש פסולים. mekadesh psulim. So the
גמרא Gemara says now it's a pretty interesting, I think it's a
חידוש, chiddush, especially conceptually, but the גמרא Gemara says מאי קמשמע לן
תנינא? Mai kamashma lan tanina? That exact ברייתא Braisa that had
who was it, was it רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda saying? That exact
ברייתא Braisa says who had רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi saying? Excuse me
a minute.
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. That exact ברייתא Braisa that had רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda saying if you spill the blood, you don't get to
leave the limbs on the altar. That said,
but if the inner blood was on the outer or the outer
on the inner, etc., you do get to leave the limbs on
the altar. And presumably that was going even according to רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. It was רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So רש"י Rashi is
saying, but because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda didn't argue, whatever, we're assuming
that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would agree with that scenario and only
disagrees with the spilled blood
scenario.
It wasn't necessarily before.
Maybe, I don't know. Obviously, people were being sloppy because things were
going wrong, so who knows? One כהן kohen did this, the other
כהן kohen did that. One כהן kohen was tasked with putting the
limbs on the altar, the כהן kohen who was tasked with putting
the blood on the altar got confused and thought it was other
blood and brought it inside or whatever. So yes, I mean, Michael
is correct that that line in the previous quote was actually from
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, but the גמרא Gemara assumes רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda agrees with that because he only excludes the case of spilling
the blood. So because one of the scenarios in the case before
was blood above, below, below, above, and also inner blood on the
outer, outer blood on the inner, so it's exactly the case of
that of what we quoted, of that ברייתא. Braisa. So what type
of a חידוש chiddush is it? מאי קמשמע לן תנינא הניתנין בפנים
Mai kamashma lan tanina hanitnin bifnim etc. So the גמרא Gemara says
no. אי מהתם הוה אמינא הני מילי דם. Ei mehatam havah amina
hani mili dam. That's true. That is talking about blood and that
is explicit דחזי ליה. dechazi lei. Because at least blood sometimes goes
on the inner altar. If you have an inner חטאת chatas like
on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you put the blood on the inner
altar. אבל קומץ דלא חזי ליה. Aval kometz delo chazi lei. But
let's say you made your mistake with the מנחה. mincha. Okay, and
you put the
handbreadth on the inner altar to burn it on the top of
the inner altar. Now, no one ever does that. It actually is
a מפורש פסוק meforash pasuk you're not allowed to do that. לא
תעלה עליו. Lo taaleh alav. What is the פסוק? pasuk? Michael, help
me. דלא חזי
ליה. Delo chazi lei. רש"י Rashi I think quotes the פסוק. pasuk.
לא
תעלו עליו קטורת זרה ועולה ומנחה. Lo ta'alu alav ketoret zarah ve'olah
u'mincha. Okay, so it explicitly says don't put a מנחה mincha on
it. דלא חזי ליה. delo chazi leh. So for that case
אימא לא, eima lo, I might think that if you did put
the קומץ, komets, it's meaningless and then if you wanted to, you
know, burn and if the rest of the מנחה mincha was being
burned, you would have to take it down, קא משמע לן, ka
mashma lan, okay, that's not the way... Wait, actually
what do I mean the rest of the מנחה mincha being burned?
I take that back. I guess the קומץ komets itself being burned.
Right, you're right because you don't burn the rest of the מנחה,
mincha, right? So you're right. So it's about the קומץ komets itself.
Okay, so you're burning the קומץ komets itself and now it's really
a חידוש chiddush because if you think about it, think about this
for a minute, okay? It's one thing if you got limbs on
the altar and the קרבן korban isn't valid and you're saying leave
the limbs. You're not directly violating anything, okay, but if you actually
have the קומץ komets burning on the inner altar, okay, and you're
gonna say let it continue to burn, the פסוק pasuk says לא
תעלה עליו, lo ta'aleh alav, you know, עולה ומנחה. olah u'mincha. So
it's actually and you're now allowing a מנחה mincha to continue to
burn on the altar. And that's what we would have to say,
yeah, לכתחילה לא תעלה עליו, lechatchila lo ta'aleh alav, but if you
already put it on, you can leave it on. So that's a
pretty big חידוש, chiddush, not just because you normally don't have a
קומץ komets on the inner altar, but because you're explicitly violating a
פסוק, pasuk, it would seem by leaving it there, and nevertheless, you're
allowed to leave it there. אבל קומץ דלא חזי ליה אימא לא
קא משמע לן Aval komets delo chazi leh eima lo ka mashma
lan that you're allowed to leave the קומץ komets there. מיתיבי Meisvei
says the גמרא, Gemara, I'll challenge you.
Any difference if you did it בשוגג beshogeg or במזיד? bemezid?
No, I mean I don't know, it doesn't seem to be. מיתיבי
Meisvei says the גמרא, Gemara, קטורת זרה שעלה לגבי מזבח תרד. Ketoret
zarah she'alah legabei mizbe'ach tered. We have a ברייתא braita that says
by the קטורת, ketoret, the other thing that you're not supposed to
put on the inner altar, okay, so קטורת זרה, ketoret zarah, excuse
me, קטורת ketoret you can, but a קטורת זרה, ketoret zarah, a
foreign קטורת, ketoret, a קטורת ketoret that you're not licensed to put
on it, okay, if it was put on the inner altar, which
is again a direct violation of that verse, okay, תרד, tered, it
has to come down. I'm sorry, קטורת זרה שעלה למזבח החיצון, Ketoret
zarah she'alah lemizbe'ach hachitzon, I'm sorry, I don't know where my head
is today, I keep on misreading this. Okay, so you actually brought
it on the outer altar, excuse me, למזבח חיצון. lemizbe'ach hachitzon. Wait,
no, no, I was right the first time. Okay, I was right.
I'm sorry. Thank you, thank you. I was right the first time.
מיתיבי קטורת זרה שעלה לגבי מזבח תרד. Meisvei: Ketoret zarah she'alah legabei
mizbe'ach tered. You have to bring it down. So it's sort of
like the sin of נדב ואביהוא, Nadav ve'Avihu, okay, it was exactly
the אש זרה, esh zarah, it was exactly the קטורת ketoret that
they were not licensed to bring and here it says you bring
it down. So why would you have to take the קטורת ketoret
off and you can leave the קומץ komets of the מנחה mincha
on? They're exactly in the same פסוק. pasuk.
So which מזבח mizbe'ach do you put it on?
So we're assuming it means, okay, שאין לך מקדש פסולים אלא מזבח
החיצון וראוי לו she'ein lecha mekadesh pesulim ela mizbe'ach hachitzon vera'ui lo
to keep on reading. We're assuming it means the inner
מזבח. mizbe'ach. The only thing that sanctifies invalid קרבנות korbanot that allows
the limbs to continue to be burned is the outer altar and
things that are fit for it. I won't unpack the word "things
that are fit for it" right now. The inner altar, it seems
to be saying, does not have this effect. Okay, and maybe the
inner altar works for blood, but the inner altar is not going
to have this effect for incense and presumably for the מנחה. mincha.
So how do you say that the inner altar does work for
the מנחה mincha in a similar capacity? So the גמרא Gemara says
חיצון אין פנימי לא, hachitzon in, penimi lo, which is a very
reasonable read. And the phrase, you know, so this power to allow
the thing to continue to burn is primarily the outer altar. Maybe
the inner altar with blood but not with קטורת, ketoret, not with
מנחה. mincha. So the גמרא Gemara says תריץ הכי. Taretz hachi. No,
reread the ברייתא braita this way: קטורת זרה שעלה למזבח החיצון תרד.
Ketoret zarah she'alah lemizbe'ach hachitzon tered. That I agree with you, that
if it's the incense is on the... no, excuse me, the point
is not the inner altar is never good.
The reading is the following:
מזבח הקטורת Mizbe'ach Haketoret is inside, right?
Yes, but it's קטורת זרה, ketoret zarah, it's a non-licensed קטורת. ketoret.
That's why it's לא תעלה עליו קטורת זרה ועולה ומנחה. lo ta'aleh
alav ketoret zarah ve'olah u'mincha. Okay, so we read it as the
unlicensed קטורת ketoret is on the inner altar, that doesn't help. The
only thing that works is the outer altar. That's the way we
read it. The inner altar does not work for קטורת, ketoret, for
מנחה, mincha, etc. Now we're going to reread the ברייתא braita to
say this way: קטורת זרה שעלה למזבח החיצון תרד. Ketoret zarah she'alah
lemizbe'ach hachitzon tered.
If you put the unlicensed קטורת ketoret on the outer altar, תרד,
tered, שאין מזבח חיצון מקדש פסולים אלא הראוי לו. she'ein mizbe'ach hachitzon
mekadesh pesulim ela hara'ui lo. Why? It wasn't a comment on the
inner altar. It was a comment that the קטורת ketoret on the
outer altar doesn't let it remain there. You know why? 'Cause קטורת
ketoret doesn't belong on the outer altar. Okay, so don't read it's
because the inner altar doesn't work. That's the way you were reading
the ברייתא. braita. That's wrong. The reading of the ברייתא braita is
קטורת ketoret doesn't work on the outer altar because it doesn't belong
on the outer altar. So that's why you can't leave it. So
okay, so what is the story about the inner altar? Oh, well
as far as the inner altar is concerned, והפנימי בין ראוי לו
בין שאין ראוי לו. ve'hapenimi bein ra'ui lo bein she'ein ra'ui lo.
You know what? The inner altar is even better than the outer
one, the exact opposite way you wanted to read it. The inner
one works not only for blood which you put on it, but
it even will work for a מנחה mincha and קטורת זרה ketoret
zarah which don't belong on it. Okay, so why is the inner
altar more powerful? powerful now than the outer altar. It's the opposite
of how we were reading the ברייתא braita, *baraisa*. מאי טעמא *mai
ta'ama*, what's the reason? האי רצפה והאי כלי שרת *hai ritzpa v'hai
kli shares*. The outer altar is like the floor of the בית
המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, which is a funny idea, but the point is
it's not movable. And because it's not movable, it's part of the
structure, okay, it does not have, this is a little funny, if
you were to ask me what do I think is more sanctified,
the structure of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* or the כלים *keilim*,
not so clear how I would answer, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
means the structure's like permanent, it's more like there for a permanent
way. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually says that it's the כלים
*keilim* that have a higher sanctity. Now not any כלי *kli*, you
know, this it's both because it's a combination of an altar and
a כלי שרת *kli shares*. A מזבח mizbei'ach *mizbeach* and a כלי
שרת *kli shares*, whereas the outer altar does not have a status
of a כלי שרת *kli shares*. So because of that the inner
altar has this higher sanctity, you might have just said it's higher
because it's on the
inner, yeah. Okay anyway, and therefore it works even for these things
that don't belong on it. Okay, so we had one way of
reading the ברייתא braita *baraisa* which is anything on the inner altar
other than blood does not validate the sacrifice to allow the things
to continue to burn, okay, which is a pretty reasonable read of
the ברייתא braita *baraisa*. But in order to make it consistent with
what's being said, we actually say, no, the outer altar doesn't work
for קטורת ketoret. *ktoret*. קטורת *ktoret* doesn't belong on the outer altar.
The inner altar works not only for blood, it works it works
even for a מנחה *mincha* and even for a קטורת *ktoret* which
doesn't belong there, קטורת זרה *ktoret zara*, which are an explicit violation
of לא lo. תעלה עליו קטורת זרה ועולה ומנחה *lo sa'aleh alav
ktoret zara v'olah u'mincha*, even though that was violated, somehow once it's
on there it doesn't continue to be violated and it has and
even though those things are completely not fit for it, its sanctity
is such that they're allowed to continue to burn. So that's a
pretty huge חידוש chiddush. *chiddush* that it's so much better than the
outer altar.
So let's say I decided to like burn, you know, forget the
blood, like I decided to actually burn the meat on the inner
altar.
Well, that is an interesting question, which actually רשי Rashi. *Rashi* and
תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* and the שיטה מקובצת *Shita Mekubetzet* I think were
sort of debating a little bit and I, you know, hadn't totally
unpacked it. Would it mean that because these things are there you're
allowed to leave like if you're allowed to but presumably if you're
allowed to leave the, you know, the מנחה *mincha* to continue to
burn, which is a direct violation, right,
presumably you would if somebody put meat on there, you'd allow the
meat to continue to burn as well, right, I would think, but
anyway, I was wondering the exact same thing. Okay, let's take a
look at the next משנה Mishna *mishna*.
Weren't we just yesterday about the but I didn't have this in
mind, about I thought it might be more on a higher level.
Oh, did you?
And I thought you said conceptually you didn't think the inner altar...
yeah... could be you're right and could be I was wrong, I
don't remember that exact exchange. Right, right. Okay, okay, yeah, yeah. Okay.
Oh no, I think you were asking
about I now vaguely remember. Anyway, if you did ask that, then
you were right. Okay, I thought maybe you were asking something a
little different, but anyway, it's fine. Okay, let's look at the next
משנה Mishna *mishna*. השוחט את הזבח hashochet es hazevach לזרוק דמו בחוץ
*hashochet et hazevach lizrok damo bachutz*. Finally, since we dealt with all
these other invalidities, right, first we deal with the thought invalidity of
שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*. Then we deal with the invalidity of things
like not catching the blood, you know, not putting the blood in
the right place, having the כהן *kohen* invalid because he's in a
different status. Okay, and now we finally circle back to the thought
invalidity of פיגול pigul *piggul*, which is the one that we've been
referencing already for who knows how many days and we're going to
continue to reference throughout the מסכת *masechet*. The גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* really
loves talking about פיגול pigul *piggul*. Okay, so finally we're there, here
at this משנה Mishna, *mishna*. השוחט את הזבח *hashochet et hazevach*. You
slaughter the sacrifice. Now this is a thought invalidity applies even at
the time of שחיטה shechita, *shechita* like the שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*.
It's not just about, you know, the status of the כהן *kohen*
and so on. Okay, so you slaughter the sacrifice, לזרוק דמו בחוץ
*lizrok damo bachutz*, and when you're doing it you're intending to throw
the blood outside the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. So this is מחשבת
חוץ *machsheves chutz*, which is like פיגול pigul *piggul*. It invalidates, but
it doesn't make the meat כרת kares *kares*.
או מקצת דמו בחוץ *o miktzas damo bachutz*, or even some of
the blood you're going to throw outside, even if you're going to
throw most of the blood in the right place. להקטיר lehaktir, אימוריו
בחוץ *lehaktir imurav bachutz*, you're going to burn the fats or whatever
outside the temple. או מקצת אימוריו בחוץ *o miktzas imurav bachutz*, even
just some of them. לאכול le'echol בשרו בחוץ *le'echol besaro bachutz*, you're
going to do it your thinking that you're going to eat the
meat outside. או כזית kezayis מבשרו בחוץ *o kezayit mibsaro bachutz*, even
one olive's worth. או לאכול כזית kezayis מעור האליה בחוץ *o le'echol
kezayit me'or ha'alyah bachutz*, or even just to eat a כזית *kezayit*
of the skin of the fat tail, which you know, we'll see
now. That's going to be a discussion, I'm that's going to be
most of what today's דף *daf* is to do is discuss this
fat tail line. I will just tell you in the easy way
to read the משנה Mishna *mishna* is that the fat of the
fat tail gets burnt, the skin of the fat tail technically speaking
can be eaten, is part of the things the no, like the
skin, like you know when you like you know when you eat
chicken you got the skin and then you got the stuff underneath,
I mean again, I don't know, I've never really looked at a
fat tail. But anyway, it's just like it's filled with fat, but
it's not fat exposed to the air, there's a layer of skin
around it. Okay, so you're eating the so that presumably is something
that you can eat, the fat goes on the altar. Okay. Okay,
now maybe usually you'd throw it all on the—so they
usually skin skin it and
then put—yeah, that's an interesting question. Maybe sometime—yeah, you're right. It obviously
would be, you know, how you're going to supposed to skin a
fat tail? So presumably you would actually maybe מן הסתם you would
throw the whole thing on. Okay, but technically speaking, you're allowed to
eat the skin of it. That seems to be the חידוש. chiddush
And therefore, if you planned to eat the skin outside, that's—even that
is considered the meat of the קרבן, korban, then it's—all those things
are thoughts that invalidate and פסול pasul the meat is invalidated but
אין בו כרת ein bo kares but there's no כרת kares. for
eating the meat. Okay, for eating the meat that, you know, after
you've had those thoughts. Now I want to again point out that
the thoughts of פיגול pigul, we've mentioned this before, but it bears
repeating, the thoughts of פיגול pigul, are during the עבודות, avodos, the
four classic עבודות, avodos, right? שחיטה, קבלה, kabala, הולכה, holacha, זריקה, zarika,
etc. But the thoughts are only relating to things that are considered
acts of eating. Eating the meat or the eating of the altar.
What eating does the altar do? דם Dam is put on it
and the fats and limbs that are put on it. So the
the content of the thought has to relate to either to some—to
one of the eating acts. Okay, anyway, so if it's a thought
about outside, it's invalid but no כרת.
kares I'm sorry, so but this is—but but I think to eat
the אימורים imurim is that included?
No, well, that's what we're going to discuss. Presumably not.
I thought פיגול pigul, was just about time, not about—No,
so this is the counterpart to פיגול, pigul which is חוץ למקומו.
chutz limkomo. Because it's not real פיגול, pigul you don't get כרת
kares for eating the meat as opposed to the next case, okay,
so
which is—which is the real פיגול, pigul okay. If it is לזרוק
דמו למחר, lizrok damo lemachar, let me finish. It is לזרוק דמו
למחר מקצת דמו למחר, lizrok damo lemachar mikzas damo lemachar, if it's
about throwing the blood tomorrow, even some of the blood, להקטיר אימוריו
למחר מקצת אימוריו למחר lehaktir imurav lemachar mikzas imurav lemachar or the
fats or whatever, או לאכול בשרו למחר כזית מבשרו למחר o le’echol
besaro lemachar kezayis mibesaro lemachar or to eat the meat or כזית
of the meat on the next day. By the way, that wouldn't
apply to a שלמים. shlamim. The irony is that the case in
the תורה Torah of פיגול pigul is a שלמים shlamim which is
eaten for two days. So if you're dealing with a שלמים, shlamim,
your intent has to be to eat the meat on the third
day, not on the—not on the next day, on the למחר lemachar
as they would say. Anyway, או לאכול כזית מעור האליה למחר, o
le’echol kezayis me’or ha’alya lemachar, even just to eat a כזית of
this fat—of the skin of the fat tail, in all those cases
פיגול וחייבים עליו כרת. pigul vechayavim alav kares. In all those cases,
it is פיגול pigul and full פיגול pigul, and the—whatever, real פיגול
pigul and you would get כרת kareit not for having those thoughts,
but if you were to then afterwards eat the meat. Okay, let's
take a look. The גמרא'ס Gemara’s first focus is all going to
be about the fat tail. סברוה עור אליה כאליה דמי. Savruha or
alya k’alya dami. Now the גמרא Gemara says as opposed to the
way I read the משנה Mishna, or I preferred to read the
משנה Mishna that the the skin of the fat tail is like
the fat tail. And in the sense that, you know, that you
would burn it on the altar, okay? And if you would not
burn it, you would be like considered to not fully burnt the
fat—not burnt all the fats, okay? Okay, so if that's true, והא
כמחשב מאכילת מזבח לאכילת אדם, veha kamachashev me’achilas mizbeach l’achilas adam, so
the גמרא Gemara says, so then why is that a פיגול pigul
thought that invalidates? That's like if I thought to let's—you know, let's
say I thought to eat the real fat, you know, tomorrow. But
that's—but that's not just saying the the eating is going to take
place in the wrong time or the wrong place, it's a different
type of an eating. I'm taking the altar's eating and I'm thinking
about it in terms of my eating, okay? Let's say I would
say that I'm going to drink the דם dam of the of
the קרבן korban tomorrow, right? Is that a thought that invalidates? Presumably,
I have to think about the stuff I would eat, that I'm
going to eat it on the wrong—on the wrong time. The stuff
the altar would eat, the altar will eat it on the wrong
time. If this is really the—if the skin of the fat tail
is really like the fat tail, then why does my thought about
me eating it invalidate? והא כמחשב מאכילת מזבח לאכילת אדם, Veha kamachashev
me’achilas mizbeach l’achilas adam, your thought is about something the altar should
eat in terms of your eating it. Why is that a problem?
אמר שמואל הא מני רבי אליעזר היא דאמר מחשב מאכילת מזבח לאכילת
אדם ומאכילת אדם לאכילת מזבח. Amar Shmuel ha meni Rabbi Eliezer hi
d’amar machashev me’achilas mizbeach l’achilas adam u’me’achilas adam l’achilas mizbeach.
Yes, it's—this is the position, it's—it's a minority position, but it's the
position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says that type of a
thought invalidates. And if you were to think I'm going to burn
the meat that I should be eating, I'm going to burn that
meat on the altar tomorrow, that would also invalidate. דתנן, Detnan, we
taught, השוחט את הזבח if somebody slaughters—it's a פיגול, pigul
right, השוחט את הזבח לאכול דבר שאין דרכו לאכול, hashochet es hazevach
le’echol davar she’ein darko le’echol, but you plan to eat something normally
of the meat that normally wouldn't be eaten. You thought you were
going to drink the דם, dam, eat the fat, you know, that
normally would go on the altar, או להקטיר דבר שאין דרכו להקטיר,
o lehaktir davar she’ein darko lehaktir, or you're going to burn something
on it that normally wouldn't be burned. I'm going to burn the
fat that—the meat that I—that's my meat to eat. In all those
cases כשר, kasher, you do not make it פיגול pigul even though
your thought was to do it at the wrong time. ורבי אליעזר
פוסל, veRabbi Eliezer posel, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer invalidates. So says
the גמרא, Gemara במאי אוקימתא, bemai okimta, so what do you want
to say, our משנה'ס Mishna’s going like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, like
רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, look at the end
of the משנה, Mishna. meaning the משנה Mishna that we're going to
read this משנה, Mishnah, you know, this משנה'ס Mishna’s coming up in
a few days and this משנה Mishnah, is really part two of
our משנה. Mishnah Okay, the second part of our משנה Mishnah is
says the following, השוחט זה הכלל, hashochet ze haklal, this is a
principle... It’s coming up in tomorrow. כ״ט ע״ב Kaf Tet Amud Bet
is the second part of our משנה, Mishnah and immediately the next
line following our משנה, Mishnah, the immediate next משנה Mishnah. reads the
following: זה הכלל, Zeh haklal, this is the rule: כל השוחט והמקבל
והמוליך והזורק, Kol hashochait v'hamikabel v'hamolich v'hazoraik, anybody who slaughters or catches
blood or brings it or throws it, לאכול דבר שדרכו לאכול ולהקטיר
דבר שדרכו להקטיר, le'echol davar shedarko le'echol ul'haktir davar shedarko l'haktir, if
it is about eating something that you normally eat or burning something
that is normally burned, so דבר שדרכו לאכול, davar shedarko le'echol, so
then you make it פיגול pigul. or you make it פסול pasul
depending on whether it's a thought of wrong place or wrong time.
But the משנה Mishnah's is clear that after listing all these examples
of the blood and the fat and whatever, the next line of
the משנה Mishnah says this only works if it is the thing
that's normally eaten or the thing that's normally burned, which is exactly—I
mean,
by do—I mean, like
let's say—no, לאכול is the contrast to להקטיר, Lehaktir like we're talking
about קטורת. להקטיר means like the burning of the fats or whatever.
Okay. So—no, no, no, anyway—no, the hooves or some—no, no, no, because
if you look exactly at the previous משנה, Mishnah anyway whatever. Okay.
So דבר שדרכו לאכול davar shedarko le'echol אין, in, שאין דרכו לאכול
she-ain darko le'echol לא. That's exactly, that's exactly
the way of articulating a non-רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer position, okay, that
it's only you're eating things that you're supposed to be eating or
the altar is, you know, it's a thought about the altar having
things burn on it that are supposed to be burned on it.
That's exactly the point of the next line of the משנה. Mishnah
So אתיא לרבנן, Atya l'rabbanan, so that's a רבנן Rabbanan position, the
exact next line. So רישא רבי אליעזר, reisha Rabbi Eliezer, the רישא
reisha that speaks about the fat tail. You're going to say that
the reason that is makes it פיגול pigul is because it's like
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that even though it's an altar eating, it
makes it פיגול pigul if you think about your eating it. So
the begin—our משנה's Mishnah רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer וסיפא רבנן v'seifa Rabbanan
in the exact next line of the משנה Mishnah you're going to
tell me contradicts this and is the רבנן? Rabbanan? So אמר ליה,
Amar lei, אין. in. Yeah, why not? Okay.
Which seems like a terrible answer, but of course you always wonder
like, you know, maybe sometimes it's true because the משנה Mishnah's was
edited by different sources and different sources were put together. You know,
so therefore maybe, yeah. Our משנה Mishnah, speaks about the fat tail
as a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer position, the exact next line, although
the funny thing is the next line says זה הכלל. zeh haklal.
זה הכלל Zeh haklal is usually coming to tell you, here's the
principle about the specific cases I just mentioned a second ago. Anyway,
that's a weak answer, but that's the answer. Our משנה mishnah that
speaks about the fat tail is the position of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, although the exact next line of the משנה mishnah directly rejects
that idea and says אין מחשבין מאכילת מזבח לאכילת אדם. ain m'chashvin
m'achilat mizbeach l'achilat adam. That's read number one. Okay. אמר ליה, Amar
lei, אין. in. רב הונא אמר, Rav Huna amar, עור אליה לאו
כאליה דמי. or alya lav k'alya dami. Okay, thank you. He says
actually the skin is not like the fat tail and you don't
burn the skin or maybe, I don't know again, Michael's question is
a good one. Does it mean that you always remove the skin
or does it mean you don't have to burn the skin? But
anyway halachically it is not part of the fat tail and you
can eat the skin and it is exactly part of what a
person is included in the meat that a person is allowed to
eat. Okay, and that's why your thought about eating it at the
wrong time makes it פיגול. pigul. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, מאי טעמא דרב הונא? Mai ta'ama d'Rav Huna? What's
the reason of רב הונא? Rav Huna? חלבו האליה תמימה. Chelbo ha'alya
temimah. So it's funny, a part of the verse says האליה תמימה,
ha'alya temimah, the complete fat tail, but it says its fat. So
the "it" there, the possessive, you know, the "it" refers to the
קרבן, korban, the קרבן's korban's fat, the entire אליה. alya. Okay, but
because it describes it as fat, so you could say it's saying
the whole אליה's alya's defined as fat, but he is going to
read it no, only the fat of the אליה alya is what
goes on the altar ולא עור האליה. v'lo or ha'alya. The חלב
chelev of the אליה, alya, not the עור or of the אליה.
alya. And then our משנה's mishnah a very easy read. It's telling
you the skin of the אליה, alya, yes, I know actually that's
the whole חידוש chiddush of the משנה, mishnah to let you know
that even the skin of the אליה alya is not fat and
technically is meat that can be eaten and therefore that's why you
can make it פיגול pigul. when you think you're going to eat
it
later. Okay. רב חסדא אמר, Rav Chisda amar, לעולם עור האליה כאליה
דמי. le'olam or ha'alya k'alya dami. רב חסדא Rav Chisda goes back
to שמואל's Shmuel's position. Okay, you know, you know the skin is
like the אליה. alya. So that's true, why when you eat from
it does—your thought to eat from it does it invalidate? והכא במאי
עסקינן באליה של גדי. v'hacha b'mai askinan b'alya shel gdi.
We're not talking about a sheep's fat tail. If it were a
sheep's fat tail the thought would not invalidate. You're right, this is
not a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer position. It needs to be a
human eating about a human eating. Okay, but we're talking about a
goat and since we're talking about a goat, a goat you don't
put the tail on the altar, you eat the tail of the
goat, you're allowed to, and that's why it's—this is relevant. Now the
problem with this is that the phrase אליה של גדי alya shel
gdi makes no sense because goats do not have a fat tail.
If you ever saw a goat, it's got a little tail. Okay,
so it's not the הלכה, halacha, this is an often a misconception
that people have that the goat has a fat tail and the
sheep has a fat tail but you only put the sheep's fat
tail on the altar not the goat's fat tail. Goat doesn't have
a fat tail, okay. So it's like say—I you know, I don't
know what it's like saying. You don't put the fifth leg of
the goat on the altar. Goat, it's got a little tail. Okay.
There, so it's not the הלכה, halakha, this is an often a
misconception that people have, that the goat has a fat tail and
the sheep has a fat tail, but you only put the sheep's
fat tail on the altar, not the goat's fat tail. Goat doesn't
have a fat tail, okay? So it's like say, I don't know
what it's like saying, you don't put the fifth leg of the
goat on the altar, there is no fifth leg. Anyway, but that's,
so it's really a very hard read of the משנה mishnah because
the משנה mishnah could have referred to a goat's tail as the
skin of the fat tail. There is no fat tail of a
goat. So I really don't understand what the גמרא Gemara was thinking,
but anyway, that's how he's reading it, that our משנה mishnah is
talking about the tail of the goat and that's why it's a
פיגול piggul. thought when you think about when you're going to eat
it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. כולו כשמואל
לא אמרי, Kulo k'Shmuel lo amri, everybody now, why did each one
of these תנאים Tannaim take one position over, אמוראים Amoraim take one
of these positions over the other? So we didn't say like שמואל
Shmuel the other two to say that because רישא רבי אליעזר וסיפא
רבנן לא מוקמי, reisha Rabbi Eliezer v'seifa Rabbanan lo mokmi, they didn't
want to say the beginning of the משנה mishnah is רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer and the end of the משנה mishnah is the רבנן,
Rabbanan, right? They didn't want to say that. That's a wild—why should
the first part of the משנה mishnah think that yes you could
have a thought from מזבח mizbei'ach. to אדם adam and the second
part say explicitly you can't? כרב הונא לא אמרי, K'Rav Huna lo
amri, they didn't want to say so
שמואל Shmuel and רב חסדא Rav Hisda who was—רב חסדא Rav Hisda
didn't want to say like רב הונא Rav Huna who said the—what
I think is the simplest read, that the skin is not like
the fat tail. They didn't want to say that. או עור עליה
קעליה דמי קמשמע להו o or alya ka'alya dami kamashma lehu because
exactly שמואל Shmuel and רב הונא Rav Huna are—רב חסדא Rav Hisda
are of the position that the skin is like the fat tail.
So that's why they didn't adopt the position that the skin wasn't
like the fat tail. רב חסדא מאי טעמא לא אמר? Rav Hisda
mai ta'ama lo amar? Now, if you hold that the skin
is like the fat tail, why did שמואל Shmuel not want to
say like רב חסדא, Rav Hisda, you know, that we're talking about
the tail of the goat? Okay. כרב חסדא לא אמרי, K'Rav Hisda
lo amri, why? Where am I? מאי טעמא לא אמר? מאי קמשמע
לן mai ta'ama lo amar? mai kamashma lan because they would say,
because then what would be the point of the משנה mishnah to
tell you עור עליה קעליה דמי? or alya ka'alya dami? The point
of the משנה mishnah would tell you that it is—the skin is
like the אליה. alya. Now this עור עליה קעליה דמי or alya
ka'alya dami means—it's confusing. It doesn't mean the same thing it meant
a minute ago. Let me just double check
רש"י.
Rashi. הא דרב חסדא למה לי למיתנייה? Ha d'Rav Hisda lamah li
l'mitneih?
אכילת אדם. achilat adam.
Oh.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So if it's basically to tell you—if we're only
talking about the, again, it's a bizarre idea that we're to call
this the skin of the fat tail of a goat because a
goat doesn't have a fat tail. But here the עור עליה קעליה
דמי or alya ka'alya dami does not mean the fat tail of
the sheep and it would be something you would burn on the
מזבח. Here we'd be saying if the משנה mishnah is talking about
the tail of a goat, then the whole חידוש chiddush? of the
משנה mishnah would be that the skin of the tail of the
goat is edible, you know, and it's not like a bone that
isn't edible. Like what I was saying before, if you had a
thought to eat the hoof or the bone, that would not invalidate.
It has to be a thought about something that's edible, something that's
meat. So according to this idea that we're not talking about the
fat tail of a sheep and only talking about the tail of
a goat, what's the חידוש? chiddush That a tail of a goat
is edible? That would be the only חידוש chiddush that there would
be. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay now,
so that's why they didn't say like רב חסדא. Rav Hisda. So
כרב חסדא מאי
טעמא לא אמר? K'Rav Hisda mai ta'ama lo amar? Now, if according
to רב חסדא Rav Hisda that we're talking about the tail of
a goat, מאי קמשמע לן, mai kamashma lan, what would it be
telling me? עור עליה קעליה דמי Or alya ka'alya dami that the
tail—now here this means something different, you know again, that the skin
of the tail of a goat is like edible? Is that the
point? So תניא, tanya, but we—that's implicit in a ברייתא, braita, תנינא
tanina in a משנה mishnah rather I think, ואלו שעורותיהן כבשרן. v'eilu
she'oroteihen k'visran. The following things when it comes to טומאה, tumah, their
skin is like the meat and the skin also is מקבל טומאה.
mikabel tumah. Now the only thing that's מקבל טומאה mikabel tumah is
something that's edible. So saying the skin is like the meat is
saying the following things the skin is considered to be edible. Okay,
so which are those things?
ואלו שעורותיהן כבשרן עור שתחת האליה, V'eilu she'oroteihen k'visran, or she-tachat ha-alya,
the skin that's underneath the fat tail. So it's explicit that it's
considered edible. So if your reading is that we're talking about the
fat tail of a goat, then the only חידוש chidush is that
it's considered edible because if you had a thought about something that
wasn't edible you wouldn't invalidate. But it's implicit from the laws of
טומאה tumah that it's considered edible. So why would our משנה Mishna,
have to be teaching it? So the גמרא Gemara says ורב חסדא,
v'Rav Hisda, רב חסדא Rav Hisda would say back to you—he's the
one that says we are talking about the tail of a goat—איצטריך,
itztrich, you need it. סלקא דעתך אמינא הני מילי לענין טומאה, Salka
da'atach amina hanei mili l'inyan tumah, I might have thought that when
it comes to laws of טומאה tumah I'll consider it edible. Why?
דרכיך מצטרף, d'rachich mitztaref, since it's soft, you know, it's edible enough
or maybe it's not even technically edible but it's enough like the
flesh that it creates the minimum amount to become טמא. tamei. Okay?
So maybe it by itself maybe it wouldn't become טמא tamei or
something, but maybe because it's connected to the flesh and it's soft
like the flesh, that might be enough for laws of טומאה. tumah.
אבל הכא, aval hacha, but here in terms of whether it's relevant
for eating when it comes to your thoughts, here למשחה l'moshchah it
says that the things that the כהנים kohanim should eat should be
like for anointing, which means לגדולה, l'gdula, that when you're eating should
be a respectable eating כדרך שהמלכים אוכלים, k'derech shehamelachim ochlim, eating the
way kings eat. So in that case ולא עבדי מלכים דאכלי הכי,
v'lo avdi melachim d'achli hachi, and normal kings wouldn't eat this as
would be too
lowly, it's hard to eat, okay, so maybe for the הלכות halachas
of eating a קרבן korban it wouldn't be considered to be like
food, and אימא לא, eima lo, קא משמע לן. ka mashma lan.
Okay? So according to him, the חידוש chidush is that we're talking
just about the tail of a goat, not of a sheep, and
the חידוש chiddush is that even though it might be considered difficult
to eat, it's enough legitimate eating that a thought about it invalidates
the קרבן. korban. Okay? So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
מיתיבי, meiteivi, I'll ask you: השוחט את העולה להקטיר כזית מעור שתחת
האליה. hashochet et ha'olah lehaktir k'zayit me'or shetachat ha'alyah. So here we
have a תוספתא Tosefta and it says if you שחט shacht an
עולה olah to burn up an
olive's worth of the skin that's under the אליה, alyah, חוץ למקומו
פסול ואין בו כרת, חוץ לזמנו פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת. chutz limkomo
pasul v'ein bo kareit, chutz lizmano pigul v'chayavin alav kareit. Okay? So
that's exactly what our משנה said, it directly focuses on the skin
under the fat tail. And that's a thought that about eating about
it that can make the thing פיגול. piggul אלעזר בן יהודה איש
אבלים אומר, Elazar ben Yehuda ish Evelim omer, but אלעזר בן יהודה
Elazar ben Yehuda says משום רבי יעקב, mishum Rabbi Yaakov, וכן היה
רבי שמעון בן יהודה איש כפר עיכוס אומר משום רבי שמעון: v'chen
hayah Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda ish Kfar Ichus omer mishum Rabbi Shimon:
אחד עור בית הפרסות, echad or beit haparsot, whether you're talking about
the skin that comes from the place sort of like where the
hoofs are, בבהמה דקה b'veheimah dakkah in a small animal, ואחד עור
הראש של עגל הרך v'echad or harosh shel eigel harach or even
if you're or if you're talking about the skin
on the skull from a young calf under a year, ואחד עור
שתחת האליה v'echad or shetachat ha'alyah or you're talking about the skin
under the fat tail,
וכל שמנו חכמים גבי טומאה, v'chol shemanu chachamim gabei tumah, referencing back
what we just said a minute ago, everything that's in the list
of impurity that says that in these cases the skin or the
leather whatever is like the flesh itself, okay,
it's important to say this, maybe I haven't clarified this, but just
compare the idea of eating a steak where we would never eat
the actual skin of the cow because that's leather, and eating a
chicken where we eat the skin of the animal. So sometimes the
skin is edible and sometimes it isn't. So it says anything that's
on the list of when the skin is considered
like the flesh and it's considered edible and therefore can become טמא,
tamei, and what would be included in addition to the things we've
already mentioned, והוי עור בית הבושת v'havei or beit haboshet including the
skin
of the genital area. So in all those cases, חוץ למקומו פסול
ואין בו כרת, chutz limkomo pasul v'ein bo kareit, חוץ לזמנו פיגול
וחייבין עליו כרת. chutz lizmano pigul v'chayavin alav kareit. Okay? In all
those cases, yes you would get כרת kares for. So I mean
you could make it פיגול. piggul Okay? So basically there you have
it, and it seems to be so
so big deal, so that seems to be fine.
That seems to be saying that this is considered to be edible
and it's considered to be meat etc. etc. What's your problem with
that? So the גמרא Gemara, says here's my problem. עולה אין אבל
זבח לא. olah in aval zevach lo. Because the case was it
said השוחט את העולה. hashochet et ha'olah. So that seems to be
that this is only works because if it's an עולה olah and
it is stuff that is an עולה, olah, everything is burnt on
the altar, okay? Whereas this would not be true by a something
like a שלמים. shelamim. So one minute,
so therefore it seems that the point here is, of course the
funny thing is then it's a very strange read and I looked
at the מפרשים mefarshim and I didn't understand it. If we're talking
about an עולה olah and we're talking about the problem is whether
you're burning it inside or outside, then what does it matter whether
it's the edible parts or not the edible parts? You burn everything
of the עולה. olah. So I don't really understand the read at
all. Right? You only have to distinguish between the edible and the
non-edible if you're talking about other קרבנות korbanot where you eat the
meat and you whatever. So but the גמרא's Gemara read here is,
which I don't begin to understand, okay, that we're talking only about
an עולה, olah, and therefore it says, so it seems that all
this stuff is not considered edible and the the skin of the
fat tail, it's only by an עולה olah that you burn it
on the altar, but if it was about an animal that you
eat the meat, the same הלכה halachah would not apply. And now
the גמרא Gemara will spell it out. Okay, it says like this.
עולה אין
אבל זבח לא. olah in aval zevach lo. בשלמא לרב הונא היינו
דקתני עולה. bishlama l'Rav Huna hainu d'katani olah. So for רב הונא,
Rav Huna, so remember רב הונא Rav Huna was the one who
said that we're talking about, one minute... רב
הונא Rav Huna is the one that said that the skin... hold
on, now I'm totally lost, let me check
רש"י.
Right,
so according to רב הונא, Rav Huna, רב הונא Rav Huna says
that by a by a normal קרבן, korban, only the fat would
be burnt and not the skin around it. Okay. So that's why,
and since here we're reading this to be talking about an עולה,
olah, what are you what your thoughts are about what you're going
to burn, okay, so since it's about what your thoughts are about
what you're going to burn, so only by an עולה olah does
a thought about burning the the skin of the אליה, alyah, right,
only by an עולה olah does the thought about burning the skin
of an אליה alyah invalidate. But by a other any other קרבן,
korban, the thought about burning it would not invalidate because according to
him, you eat the skin of the אליה. alyah. Okay. So according
to him that makes sense. But again, what I guess the reason
I'm just stymied here is that if we're really talking about an
עולה, olah, then I don't understand why you need to identify these
things altogether like you burn everything. So I'm not exactly getting it.
Maybe the point is you still don't burn like the hoofs or
something. So the חידוש here is that it's considered to be meat
and it's not considered to be hoofs. I guess that's the point.
Okay. So basically what we have here is, maybe I'll draw a
picture so help me conceptualize what we're saying. Okay. I don't know
why drawing a picture's going to help, but anyway. Okay. What we're
saying here is, okay, you've got like the fat tail of the
sheep. You like my fat tail? Okay. And you've got all these
other things. Okay. So if it's an עולה, olah, okay, you burn
the meat
and even this is considered to be like, you know, meat or
whatever. Okay. But you don't burn let's say the hoofs. Okay. So
what this משנה is doing, here's the hoofs I guess, okay. You
don't burn the hoofs. So what this משנה is doing is it's
saying if it was an עולה olah and you were to thought
to burn this or to burn this but not to burn the
hoofs itself, maybe the skin between the hoofs, any of that stuff
if you were to thought to burn it in the wrong time
or the wrong place, you would make it invalid, you could make
it פיגול. piggul, Okay. So that's say so according to now why
are we limiting it to talking about the case of the עולה?
olah? So according to רב הונא Rav Huna you understand because רב
הונא Rav Huna would say that since it's about we're this is
discussing the issue about when are you going to burn it on
the altar, so burning on the altar, if this was not an
עולה, olah, it wouldn't the thought about burning the skin around the
fat tail would not be a problem because if it's not an
עולה olah you don't burn the skin around the fat tail, you
eat the skin around the fat tail. For רב הונא Rav Huna
we understand why we're limiting ourselves to an עולה. olah. Okay. אבל
Aval says the גמרא, Gemara היינו דתני עולא. Hainu detani Ulla. אלא
Ella רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, מאי איריא דתני עולה, mai irya detani
olah, ליתני זבח? lisni zevach? But for רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, he
says you always burn the skin around the fat tail. And since
רב חסדא Rav Chisda says you always burn the skin around the
fat tail, say that we're talking about any sacrifice, not just about
an עולה. olah. Since this ברייתא braita is talking about burning, it's
talking about what are the things that go on the altar. So
for רב הונא, Rav Huna, it's talking it has to talk about
an עולה. olah. If it weren't an עולה olah the skin of
the fat tail would not go on the altar. But according to
רב חסדא Rav Chisda by every קרבן korban the skin of the
fat tail goes on the altar, so why are we only talking
about an עולה? olah? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר לך רב
חסדא, amar lach Rav Chisda, רב חסדא Rav Chisda would say back
to you, אי בעית אימא באליה שגדי, i ba'is eima be-alyah she-gedi,
maybe we're not talking about a about a sheep, maybe we're talking
about a goat, and by a goat, if it weren't an עולה
olah the tail wouldn't go on the altar. Only by an עולה
olah does the tail go on the altar. ואי בעית אימא Ve-i
ba'is eima תני זבח. tani zevach. Or you could just say that
the ברייתא isn't talking you know it's a wrong text of the
ברייתא, the ברייתא is not just talking about an עולה, olah, it's
really talking about every sacrifice. Now normally we hate those answers, but
ironically תוספות says that that actually is our גרסא girsa of the
תוספתא Tosefta that it's not limited to an עולה. olah. Okay. So
anyway, so this is the debate. Does the skin in general do
you say that a thought about something that should burn on the
altar that you're going to eat is part of this world of
פיגול pigul etc.? That's a debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
the חכמים. Chachamim. And number two is the question right about whether
you think that the skin of the fat tail is burned like
the fat tail itself. Okay. And in that case you know רב
הונא Rav Huna says that it is that it is not burned
and because that's and when we're talking about burning it we're only
talking about an עולה olah because in general the skin is not
burned. And רב חסדא Rav Chisda says in general the skin is
always burned together with the fat tail. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara
continues, let's move on. פסול ואין בו כרת. Pasul ve-ein bo kares.
So now we're going to get to the general principle of how
we know that פיגול pigul these הלכות halachos are פיגול, pigul
that there's two things, there's חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmno and there's חוץ
למקומו, chutz limkomo, and that one of them you get כרת kares
for for eating the meat and one of them you do not
get כרת kareth for eating the
meat. Just sort of start us with the פסוקים pesukim okay so
because there's going to be two פסוקים pesukim we're going to look
at. So one of them says like this in ויקרא ז Vayikra
zayin it says
do you have the פסוק pasuk there exactly? 7:18. 7:18. Okay. ואם
האכל יאכל V'im he'achol ye'achel ואם האכל יאכל מבשר זבח שלמיו V'im
he'achol ye'achel mibsar zevach shlamav
am I getting this right? I'm trying to do it from memory.
ואם האכל יאכל מבשר
זבח שלמיו
ביום השלישי
V'im he'achol ye'achel mibsar zevach
shlamav
bayom
hashlishi
לא ירצה Lo yeratzeh לא ירצה המקריב אותו לא
יחשב Lo yeratzeh hamakriv oto
lo yeichashev פגול יהיה Piggul yihyeh
פגול Piggul a very long פסוק. pasuk. והנפש
האוכלת ממנו
עונה תשא.
V'hanefesh ha'ochelet mimenu
avonah tisa. The גמרא Gemara is going to refer to this as
the long פסוק, pasuk, okay, about פגול. piggul. Okay, so that's one
פסוק. pasuk. It's got a lot of extra words and basically what
we're going to learn out from this is both categories, both חוץ
לזמנו chutz lizmano and חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo. The other thing of
course is that the simple meaning of it is that you're eating
from it. But the גמרא Gemara is going to say, but since
it says לא ירצה, lo yeratzeh, the קרבן korban won't be accepted.
Eating from it after it's brought cannot affect whether it's going to
be accepted, because the key in the גמרא Gemara always is that
what defines whether or not it's accepted is about the blood. So
once the blood is on the altar you can't retroactively invalidate it.
So because of the לא ירצה lo yeratzeh and because of the
assumption that the validity of the קרבן korban is only based on
the blood, we are going to say that it's not that you
actually ate from it, but that you planned to eat from it.
So that's just important point number one. And the way we are
able to do that is because we have this word יחשב, yeichashev,
which literally means it will not be reckoned onto him, considered for
him. But יחשב yeichashev can also mean to have a thought, or
it's in that, right? So therefore because of the לא ירצה lo
yeratzeh we say it means not when you're eating but when you're
thinking about eating and that's the לא יחשב. lo yeichashev. Okay, now
where are we going to get the idea of חוץ לזמנו, chutz
lizmano, I mean חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo is not clear because the
whole פסוק pasuk is talking about חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano. Okay, that's
פסוק pasuk number one. But there's another פסוק. pasuk. The other פסוק
pasuk is
in קדושים. Kedoshim. And
the other פסוק pasuk is, might as well just put it up
on the board right now, you know what, we'll put the other
פסוק pasuk on the board when we get to it. Okay, there's
a much shorter פסוק pasuk in קדושים. Kedoshim. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: מנא הני מילי? Mina hanei mili? Where
do you get the idea that there's these two categories of
פגול? piggul? אמר שמואל תרי קראי כתיבי. Amar Shmuel trei kraei ktivi.
מאי היא? Mai hi? There's two פסוקים. psukim. אמר רבה. Amar Rava.
רבה. Rava. שלישי זהו חוץ לזמנו. Shlishi zehu chutz lizmano. Okay, the
idea of שלישי, shlishi, ביום השלישי, bayom hashlishi, okay, that's the obvious
case of
חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano.
פגול זהו חוץ למקומו. Piggul zehu chutz limkomo. The irony is this
extra thing פגול יהיה piggul yihyeh seems like completely superfluous. המקריב אותו
לא יחשב לו והנפש האוכלת ממנו עונה תשא. Hamakriv oto lo yeichashev
lo v'hanefesh ha'ochelet mimenu avonah tisa. What does it have to say
פגול? piggul? Of course that's the whole name we know this by,
but what's what information is being communicated by this? So because this
is extra, we're going to read that to say there's another thing
that invalidates similar, and that's not חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, that's חוץ
למקומו. chutz limkomo. Now what's of course so disturbing is that if
we anchor the idea of חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo on the words
פגול יהיה, piggul yihyeh, but חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo isn't what is
פגול. piggul. פגול piggul is the חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano. But anyway
the extra phrase here tells us חוץ
למקומו. chutz limkomo. Okay, so
now if that's true, how do you know one gets כרת kareth?
and one doesn't get כרת? kareth. Okay, והנפש האוכלת ממנו, V'hanefesh ha'ochelet
mimenu, so the next one
says... ממנו... mimenu... ממנו mimenu means only one of them עונה תשא.
avonah tisa. עונה תשא avonah tisa means כרת. kareth. So only if
you eat only if you eat from one of these two do
you get כרת. kareth זהו חוץ לזמנו
למעוטי חוץ למקומו. zehu chutz lizmano l'ma'utei chutz limkomo.
You only get כרת kareth by eating the חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano
not the חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo. ואימא והנפש האוכלת ממנו זהו חוץ
למקומו ולמעוטי חוץ לזמנו? V'eima v'hanefesh ha'ochelet mimenu zehu chutz limkomo u'lma'utei
chutz lizmano?
Why what makes you say that this only refers to the wrong
timeline? This refers to one, that I agree to you, but what
makes you say the one that it refers to that you get
כרת kareth is the חוץ לזמנו? chutz lizmano? Maybe it's the opposite.
The one it refers to that you get כרת kareth is the
חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo. ואימא והנפש האוכלת ממנו V'eima v'hanefesh ha'ochelet mimenu
no, the גמרא Gemara says מסתברא חוץ לזמנו עדיף דפתח ביה. Mistabra
chutz lizmano adif d'patach bei. No, presumably the weightier one that you
get כרת kares is the חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano. But what makes
you say the one that it refers to that you get כרת
kares is the חוץ זמנו? chutz zmano? Maybe it's the opposite? The
one it refers to that you get כרת kares is the חוץ
למקומו? chutz limkomo? ואימא והנפש האוכלת. Ve'eima vehanefesh ha'ocheles. No, the גמרא
Gemara says
מסתברא חוץ זמנו עדיף דפתח ביה. Mistavra chutz zmano adif depatach bei.
No, presumably the weightier one that you get כרת kares is the
חוץ זמנו. chutz zmano. That's the one the פסוק passuk started with:
ביום השלישי לא ירצה Bayom hashlishi lo yeratze etcetera. The גמרא Gemara
says
אדרבה חוץ למקומו עדיף דסמיך ליה. Adaraba chutz limkomo adif desamich lei.
No, but since it just mentioned the חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo, so
maybe the ממנו mimenu goes to the more most recent referent? Maybe
it goes to the חוץ למקומו? chutz limkomo? Okay, so what makes
you say that the כרת kares goes up here at the beginning?
Maybe the כרת kares, goes to the most proximate one? So the
גמרא Gemara says אמר אביי כי אתא רב יצחק בר אבדימי, Amar
Abaye ki asa Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi, so that's a really good
question. אמר רב סמיך אהא דתני תנא, Amar Rav samich aha detani
tana, כשהוא אומר. keshehu omer. So he says no, so rely on
the דרשה drasha not just on this משנה, but on the way
a תנא tana learned it out. How did the תנא tana learn
it out? כשהוא אומר, Keshehu omer, here's a different way of learning
it: שלישי בפרשת קדושים תהיו shlishi beparshas Kedoshim tihyu because it also
says יום השלישי Yom hashlishi in קדושים. Kedoshim. What's that פסוק?
passuk? You have the reference there? I didn't look it up. Does
it say?
It's somewhere in it's right at the beginning of קדושים Kedoshim I
think like ממש mamash in the first עליה. aliyah. That is yes,
this is יט ז, Yud Tes Zayin, ואם האכל יאכל ביום השלישי.
ve'im ha'achel ye'achel bayom hashlishi. This is the קדושים Kedoshim one יט
ז, Yud Tes Zayin, ואם האכל יאכל ביום השלישי.
ve'im ha'achel ye'achel bayom
hashlishi. You'll see the word a lot of the words are almost
identical, okay?
פיגול הוא לא ירצה. Piggul hu lo yeratze.
פיגול הוא לא ירצה. Piggul hu lo yeratze. It's got the key
similar phrases but it's much shorter, okay? So now what we're actually
going to say is forget what we said above. This is all
חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo and חוץ זמנו chutz zmano like it says.
יום השלישי Yom hashlishi this entire big פסוק passuk is חוץ זמנו.
chutz zmano. This extra פסוק passuk although it's ביום השלישי, bayom hashlishi,
so again it's ironic, but this extra פסוק passuk is the חוץ
למקומו chutz limkomo פסוק. passuk. And what's good about this is this
פסוק passuk doesn't mention כרת, kares okay? So this is חוץ למקומו,
chutz limkomo,
this up here is חוץ זמנו. chutz zmano. This one says כרת
kares. and this one doesn't say כרת. kares, That's a nice elegant
read, okay? שאין תלמוד לומר שהרי כבר נאמר ואם האכל יאכל מבשר
זבח השלמים ביום השלישי.
She'ein talmud lomar sheharei
kvar ne'emar ve'im ha'achel ye'achel mibesar zevach hashlamim bayom hashlishi. So we
already have the פסוק passuk from back in צו. Tzav. Why do
you need this פסוק passuk in קדושים? Kedoshim? אם אינו
עניין לחוץ זמנו תנהו עניין לחוץ למקומו.
Im eino inyan
lechutz zmano tnehu inyan lechutz limkomo.
So therefore this פסוק passuk is talking about חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo.
ומיעט רחמנא גבי נותר ואוכליו עוונו ישא למיעוטי
חוץ למקומו. Umi'et Rachmana gabi nosar ve'ochlav avono yisa lemi'utei chutz limkomo.
Now by נותר, nosar, now you really could have just stopped there
and said there's no פסוק passuk here that says what do you
call it that says כרת, kares but we're going to see in
a minute that we're also actually well whatever anyway by נותר nosar
it says which is also about about being late, but being late
in terms of actually not eating the meat, not having the thought
about it but actually not eating the meat. ואוכליו עוונו ישא. Ve'ochlav
avono yisa.
So the ואוכליו ve'ochlav here, it, okay, means that you don't always
get כרת kares for these types of things. So the that is
sort of telling you don't apply the כרת kares here of חוץ
זמנו chutz zmano to the חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo. חוץ זמנו chutz
zmano has כרת kares not חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo, okay? So now
it says like this,
one minute.
Oh oh I'm sorry okay I the point here is the next
point is one minute yeah I
was getting confused why would I need this פסוק passuk by נותר?
nosar? The reason I need the פסוק passuk by נותר nosar is
the immediate next פסוק passuk here says יט ח Yud Tes Ches
says ואוכליו עוונו
ישא. ve'ochlav avono yisa.
This is ממש mamash the next
פסוק. passuk. ואוכליו עוונו ישא כי את קודש ה' חילל
ונכרתה.
Ve'ochlav avono yisa ki es kodesh Hashem chillel
venichresa. So it's not like it doesn't mention כרת kares here. It
mentions כרת kares. in the next פסוק. passuk. You see here you
got כרת. kares. We're saying this is חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo, no
כרת. kares. But the next פסוק passuk says כרת. kares. If you
eat it you get your sin, you get כרת. karet. But what
we're going to say is this next פסוק passuk right after the
חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo is going to be talking about נותר, nosar,
okay, because that's פשט, pchat, right? The פשט pchat of this verse
is, right, if you eat on the third day is you're eating
the meat that is נותר, nosar, that is left over. So we're
going to do a really complicated thing. Since it says לא ירצה
lo yeratze it won't be accepted then this פסוק passuk cannot just
be talking about נותר nosar because again what you do with the
meat afterwards doesn't affect whether it's accepted. Since it says לא ירצה
lo yeratze it has to be talking about חוץ זמנו chutz zmano
but we already know חוץ זמנו chutz zmano so it's talking about
חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo but the פשט pchat is that it's also
talking about
נותר. nosar.
Only the נותר notar aspect you get כרת. karet You do not
get the כרת karet for the other thing that's implicit in this
פסוק, pasuk, which is the חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo. Got it? So
כרת karet. for חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo plus
נותר, notar, only the נותר notar you get כרת. karet Okay, so
now let's try to get a little bit further. Ah, okay, חוץ
למקומו. chutz limkomo. ואימא ואכליו עוונו ישא זה חוץ למקומו ולמעוטי נותר
מכרת. ve-eima ve-ochlav avono yisa zeh chutz limkomo u-le-matei notar mi-karet. No,
well maybe ואכליו ve-ochlav here means, since this really we're saying has
both ideas here, חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo plus נותר, notar, and this
is saying only נותר notar gets the כרת karet. because of ואכליו,
ve-ochlav, maybe we should actually say that this means only the חוץ
למקומו chutz limkomo gets the כרת. karet. How do you know that
this is signaling out the נותר? notar? Maybe it should be signaling
out the חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo. Okay, ואימא, ve-eima, why don't I
say ואכליו עוונו ישא זה חוץ למקומו ולמעוטי נותר מכרת? ve-eima ve-ochlav
avono yisa zeh chutz limkomo u-le-matei notar mi-karet? Maybe נותר notar is
the one that doesn't get כרת. karet. No, מסתברא נותר הוי ליה
לאוקמי בכרת, mistabra notar havei leh le-okmei be-karet, it makes sense that
נותר notar gets כרת. karet? למימר עון עון מחוץ לזמנו דדמי ליה
בז"ב. lemimar avon avon mi-chutz lizmano de-dami leh be-zav. אוי געוואלד. oy
gevalt. So the גמרא Gemara basically says, okay, how do I know
that the עוונו ישא avono yisa here means כרת? karet, Because up
here it never says כרת, karet? it just says עוונו ישא. avono
yisa. How do I know עוונו ישא avono yisa means כרת? karet
So the way I know it is because down here it says
עוונו ישא ונכרתה. avono yisa ve-nichrata. Okay,
so in general we say the way you know that you get
כרת karet. for פיגול pigul. is we know from linking פיגול to
נותר notar and here it says ונכרתה ve-nichrata that עוונו ישא avono
yisa means you get כרת. karet. You got that? That's how we
know you get כרת. karet. But in another גמרא Gemara, it says
but there's other places it says
עוונו ישא avono yisa where it's not כרת. karet? Why do we
say to link it to this meaning of it that it gets
כרת? karet. That's what a גמרא Gemara asks. And the גמרא Gemara
says well because look, there's a lot of similarities. The similarities is
ז"ב, zav, it's a cute little acronym because ז"ב zav is obviously
relevant to the מקדש, mikdash, but ז"ב zav means זמן zman and
the ב bet is, what's the ב? bet? Ta, I forgot the
ב. bet. זמן zman and
במה, bamah, okay,
that both the idea of פיגול and the idea of נותר notar
apply in a במה, bamah, they apply outside, and they're both time
related, a thought about time and actually leaving it over. So therefore
I apply this to this and not to some other פסוק pasuk
like by טומאה tumah or whatever to tell me that this means
כרת. karet Now I'm able to do that if I say that
this פסוק pasuk is talking about נותר. notar. But if I were
to say that this פסוק pasuk was talking about the חוץ למקומו,
chutz limkomo, then there wouldn't be enough comparisons to learn one out
from the other. Okay? So the גמרא, Gemara so let's read that.
It says
מסתברא נותר הוי ליה לאוקמי בכרת למימר עון עון מחוץ לזמנו דדמי
ליה בז"ב. mistabra notar havei leh le-okmei be-karet lemimar avon avon mi-chutz
lizmano de-dami leh be-zav.
In order to learn it out, you know, עון עון avon avon
to tell you that this you get כרת karet, here, these are
similar enough to learn out. Why are they similar enough to learn
out? דדמי ליה בז"ב de-dami leh be-zav
because of the הלכה halacha of זמן zman and במה. bamah. So
גמרא Gemara, says אדרבה, aderaba, let me say the opposite, חוץ למקומו
הוי ליה לאוקמי בכרת. chutz limkomo havei leh le-okmei be-karet.
It actually, if this פסוק pasuk was talking about חוץ למקומו chutz
limkomo the כרת, karet there'd be many more points of comparison with
חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano. Okay, if this was talking about the חוץ
למקומו chutz limkomo and not about נותר. notar. Why? למימר עון עון
מחוץ לזמנו דדמי ליה במקד"ש. lemimar avon avon mi-chutz lizmano de-dami leh
be-mikdash. You gotta love it. One acronym is ז"ב, zav, right, and
the other acronym is מקד"ש, mikdash, the sanctuary. What's the מקד"ש? mikdash?
So the מקד"ש mikdash is let's see if I can get this.
מ mem is מחשבה, machshava, if this was talking about חוץ למקומו
chutz limkomo then there'd be a lot of links, they'd both be
talking about things that are about your thoughts, okay, ק, kof, I'm
already stuck, what's ק? kof?
קצת, ktzat, it applies even if you, even if some of your
thought is about some of the meat you make it נותר, notar,
you make it פיגול. Okay, whereas by other things like, you know,
by טומאה, tumah, if you're מטמא metame some of the meat it
doesn't invalidate other parts of the meat, but here even a thought
about a part invalidates the whole thing. דם, dam, they're both about
thoughts about blood, okay, and שלישי, shlishi, they're both about thoughts about
like the third day, okay. So anyway, so if this was talking,
so we want to apply כרת karet from here up to. But
the גמרא Gemara, says that's no reason to say this is talking
about זב zav more than it's talking about חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo.
חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo has even more reasons to make the connection.
So we're back to our question: what makes you say the כרת
karet of this פסוק pasuk is talking about the נותר nosar of
the earlier verse and not about the חוץ למקומו? chutz limkomo? And
you can't tell me it needs to talk about נותר nosar to
allow us to make a link. We're gonna make the link either
way. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara, says אלא אמר רבי יוחנן ella
amar Rabbi Yochanan תני זבדי בר לוי tanei Zivdi bar Levi אתיא
קודש קודש. atya kodesh kodesh. It's a גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. כתיב
הכא ksiv hacha את קודש השם חילל ונכרתה es kodesh Hashem chillel
venichresa וכתיב התם uchsiv hasam
ושרפת את הנותר באש. vesarafta es hanosar ba'esh. Okay, לא יאכל כי
קודש הוא. lo ye'achel ki kodesh hu. So we know this is
talking about נותר nosar because of the word קודש השם. kodesh Hashem.
And there's another פסוק pasuk says that is explicitly about נותר nosar
that says את קודש השם חילל. es kodesh Hashem chillel.
חילל, chillel, okay. And since that פסוק pasuk is explicitly a נותר
nosar פסוק, pasuk, we know that this is a נותר nosar פסוק.
pasuk. All right, so that's how we know. כתיב הכא את קודש
השם חילל ונכרתה וכתיב התם ושרפת את הנותר באש לא יאכל, ksiv
hacha es kodesh Hashem chillel venichresa ucksiv hasam vesarafta es hanosar ba'esh
lo ye'achel, excuse me, the other פסוק pasuk is הנותר
באש לא יאכל קודש
הוא.
hanosar ba'esh lo ye'achel
kodesh hu. Okay,
so
because of קודש, kodesh, because קודש kodesh and קודש, kodesh, we know
that this פסוק pasuk is about נותר. nosar. נותר nosar is the
one you get כרת karet for. So back to it: this פסוק
pasuk is פיגול חוץ לזמנו, pigul chutz lizmano, yes כרת karet because
of עוונתה תשא. avonah sisa. This פסוק pasuk is extra חוץ למקומו,
chutz limkomo, no כרת karet mentioned for חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo, and
נותר nosar is in this פסוק. pasuk. No כרת karet, mentioned for
חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo. Next פסוק pasuk you do get כרת, karet.
but only for the נותר nosar of the previous verse, not the
חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo. And we know this is talking about נותר
nosar because ואכליו ve'ochlav is talking about one thing, and the one
thing we know it's talking about is נותר nosar because קודש השם
kodesh Hashem links to another פסוק pasuk that tells us that this
is talking about נותר. nosar. Okay, so that's how we get this
to be about נותר nosar and this to be about חוץ למקומו
chutz limkomo without
כרת. karet Let's just do a little bit more.
Where was that last verse from? שמות כ"ט. Shemos chof-tes.
Okay, ושרפת את הנותר באש. vesarafta es hanosar ba'esh. Okay, מה להלן
נותר אף כאן נותר. ma lehalan nosar af kan nosar. ומי אית
לן גבי נותר ואכליו עונו ישא למיעוטי חוץ למקומו מכרת? umi it
lan gabi nosar ve'ochlav avono yisa lemi'uti chutz limkomo mikares? Okay.
Now
he finally got it worked out. ומאי חזית דקרא אריכא בחוץ לזמנו?
umai chazis dekra aricha bechutz lizmano? Now
says the גמרא, Gemara what makes you say this big פסוק pasuk
is the חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano and that's the one you get
כרת karet, for? ושלישי דפרשת קדושים תהיו חוץ למקומו? ushelishi deparshas Kedoshim
Tihyu chutz limkomo? And בפרשת קדושים תהיו beparshas Kedoshim Tihyu and this
small פסוק pasuk from קדושים Kedoshim is the חוץ למקומו? chutz limkomo?
I concede with you, says the גמרא, Gemara, this is talking about
נותר, nosar, so what's talked about in this and only נותר nosar
you get כרת, karet. what's referred to in this part of the
פסוק pasuk is not כרת. karet. But how do I know that
this is the חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano פסוק pasuk and this is
the חוץ למקומו? chutz limkomo? And it's חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo that
doesn't get כרת. karet Maybe I should flip it? Maybe that's the
חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo and this is the חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano.
חוץ למקומו איבחנא. chutz limkomo ibachna. Okay, and
let me flip it. No, מסתברא אריכא בחוץ לזמנו. mistabra aricha bechutz
lizmano. It makes sense the big long one is חוץ לזמנו, chutz
lizmano, דגמר עון עון מנותר דדמי ליה בזב. degamar avon avon munosar
dedami lei bezav. We're back to that. Okay, that that way we
could learn if this is חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, we could say
you know that you get כרת karet. for this because it links
to נותר nosar here and they have those points of comparison: זמן
zman and במה. bamah. But if this פסוק pasuk were about חוץ
למקומו, chutz limkomo, you wouldn't be able to link it to נותר
nosar to get כרת. karet? Why wouldn't you be able to link
this to נותר nosar to get כרת? karet Because the two points
of comparison to נותר nosar are they're time-related while נותר nosar is
time-related but חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo is place-related. And that they apply
on a במה, bamah, but חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo doesn't apply on
a במה bamah because on a במה bamah there's no מקום, makom,
you can eat it anywhere. Right? So the laws of נותר nosar
and the laws of חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano apply on a במה,
bamah, but the laws of חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo don't apply on
a במה. bamah. So what allows us to link חוץ לזמנו chutz
lizmano to נותר nosar is they have two points of comparison: they're
both time-related and they both apply on a במה. bamah. But if
we flipped it and this verse was the חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo,
we would never learn out כרת karet because there's no points of
comparison with נותר. nosar. So that forces us, because we know you
get כרת karet and we need to learn that out, that pushes
us to say that this is the חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano. Okay,
so נותר דדמי ליה בזב. nosar dedami lei bezav.
אדרבה adaraba says the גמרא, אריכא בחוץ למקומו ושלישי דקדשים תהיו בחוץ
לזמנו משום דדמי לסמ"ך וקממטי ליה. aricha bechutz limkomo ushelishi dekedashim tihyu
bechutz lizmano mishum dedami lesamach vekamamtiah lei. No, maybe what I'll say
is forget your need to learn נותר nosar up here. I would
say that since the verse here has to say you only get
כרת kares for one of them, right, if it was talking about
חוץ לזמנו... chutz lizmano... then it would say, oh, נותר Nosar is
similar to חוץ לזמנו chutz l'zemano but you're only going to get
כרת kares, for נותר. Nosar. So because of the similarity, it has
them in the same verse that they're both time related, and because
it had to explicitly exclude נותר. Nosar. So it would actually make
sense to say that this is חוץ לזמנו chutz l'zemano because that's
why it would be juxtaposed to a verse by נותר Nosar to
be compared and distinguished from it. But if this was חוץ למקומו,
chutz limkomo, it would make no sense why it should be juxtaposed
to נותר. Nosar. Okay, so the גמרא's answer is you said you
want this to be חוץ לזמנו chutz l'zemano so that it could
link to נותר Nosar to tell you כרת, kares, I'm going to
tell you this should be the חוץ לזמנו chutz l'zemano because it
makes sense that that would be what would be juxtaposed to נותר.
Nosar. So, bottom line says the גמרא, this was all brilliant, okay,
you got one פסוק pasuk this, one פסוק pasuk that, not כרת,
kares but in the end you can't prove to me that this
is the חוץ לזמנו chutz l'zemano פסוק pasuk and that's the חוץ
למקומו chutz limkomo פסוק. pasuk. So we're going to end with that
for now and tomorrow we will pick up with a back to
learning it all out from the first verse. Okay, so tomorrow we're
going to learn it all out from the first verse and show
you how you get both ideas here and how you know that
only the חוץ לזמנו chutz l'zemano gets כרת and not the חוץ
למקומו. chutz limkomo. Okay, that will be for tomorrow. We leave you
on a cliffhanger.